For the next few minutes we're going to talk about energy,
خلال الأربع دقائق القادمة، سنتحدث عن الطاقة.
and it's going to be a bit of a varied talk.
وسيكون نوع من الحديث المتنوع.
I'll try to spin a story about energy,
سأحاول جعلها قصة تدور حول الطاقة،
and oil's a convenient starting place.
والنفط هو نقطة بداية مريحة.
The talk will be broadly about energy,
سيكون الحديث عامة عن الطاقة،
but oil's a good place to start.
لكن النفط هو مكان مناسب للبدء.
And one of the reasons is this is remarkable stuff.
وأحد الأسباب هو، هذه الأشياء الملحوظة.
You take about eight or so carbon atoms,
أنت تأخذ حوالي ثمانية ذرات كربون أو زيادة،
about 20 hydrogen atoms,
حوالي 20 ذرة هايدروجين،
you put them together in exactly the right way
تقوم بوضعهم معاً بالصورة الصحيحة بالضبط
and you get this marvelous liquid:
وتحصل على هذا السائل العجيب،
very energy-dense and very easy to refine
الكثيف بالطاقة وسهل جداً لصقله
into a number of very useful products and fuels.
إلى عدد من المنتجات المفيدة والوقود.
It's great stuff.
إنها أشياء عظيمة.
Now, as far as it goes,
الآن، بقدر ما تذهب،
there's a lot of oil out there in the world.
فهناك الكثير من النفط في العالم.
Here's my little pocket map
هذه هي خارطتي الصغيرة للجيب
of where it's all located.
لحيث يقبع جميعه.
A bigger one for you to look at.
وخارطة أكبر لكم لتنظروا إليها.
But this is it, this is the oil in the world.
لكن هذا كل شئ. هذا هو النفط في العالم.
Geologists have a pretty good idea of where the oil is.
لدى متخصصي الجيولجيا فكرة أفضل عن أماكن النفط.
This is about 100 trillion gallons
يوجد حوالي مائة تريلليون جالون
of crude oil
من النفط الخام
still to be developed and produced in the world today.
تنتظر التطوير والإنتاج في عالم اليوم.
Now, that's just one story about oil,
الآن، تلك هي قصة واحدة حول النفط،
and we could end it there and say,
ونستطيع إنهائها هناك ونقول،
"Well, oil's going to last forever
"حسناً، لن ينتهي النفط مطلقاً
because, well, there's just a lot of it."
لأنه، حسناً، هناك كميات ضخمة منه."
But there's actually more to the story than that.
لكن هناك المزيد لهذه القصة من ذلك.
Oh, by the way, if you think you're very far from some of this oil,
أوه، بالمناسبة، إذا اعتقدتم أنكم بعيدون جداً من أين يوجد النفط،
1000 meters below where you're all sitting
1000 متر تحت المكان الذي تجلسون عليه
is one of the largest producing oil fields in the world.
هو أحد أكبر الحقول إنتاجاً للنفط في العالم.
Come talk to me about it, I'll fill in some of the details if you want.
تعالوا وتحدثوا معي حول ذلك. سأقدم بعض التفاصيل إذا أردتم.
So, that's one of the stories of oil; there's just a lot of it.
إذاً تلك أحد القصص عن النفط. هناك الكثير منها.
But what about oil? Where is it in the energy system?
لكن ماذا عن النفط؟ أين هو في نظام الطاقة؟
Here's a little snapshot of 150 years of oil,
ها هي لمحة صغيرة لفترة 150 عاماً من النفط.
and it's been a dominant part of our energy system
وقد كان الجزء المهيمن لنظام طاقتنا
for most of those 150 years.
لمعظم تلك ال 150 عاماً.
Now, here's another little secret I'm going to tell you about:
الآن، ها هو سرّ صغير آخر سأقوم باخباركم به.
For the last 25 years,
طوال ال 25 عاماً الماضية،
oil has been playing less and less of a role
كان النفط يلعب دوراً أقل وأقل
in global energy systems.
في نظام الطاقة العالمي.
There was one kind of peak oil in 1985,
لقد كان هناك نقطة ذروة للنفط في عام 1985،
when oil represented 50 percent of global energy supply.
عندما مثّل النفط 50% من إحتياجات الطاقة عالمياً.
Now, it's about 35 percent.
الآن، يمثّل حوالي 35%.
It's been declining
إنه يتراجع،
and I believe it will continue to decline.
وأنا أعتقد أنه سيتواصل في التراجع.
Gasoline consumption in the U.S. probably peaked in 2007
على الأرجح أن إستهلاك الوقود في الولايات المتحدة كان عام 2007
and is declining.
وهو يتراجع.
So oil is playing a less significant role
إذاً فالنفط يلعب دوراً أقل أهمية
every year.
كل سنة.
And so, 25 years ago,
وعليه، قبل 25 سنة مضت،
there was a peak oil;
كان هناك نقطة ذروة في النفط
just like, in the 1920s,
تماماً مثل، في عشرينات القرن الماضي،
there was a peak coal;
كانت هناك نقطة ذروة للفحم،
and a hundred years before that,
وقبل مئات السنين قبل ذلك،
there was a peak wood.
كانت هناك نقطة ذروة للخشب.
This is a very important picture of the evolution of energy systems.
هذه صورة مهمة للغاية لتطوّر أنظمة طاقتنا.
And what's been taking up the slack in the last few decades?
ما الذي كان يحلّ محله في العقود القليلة الماضية؟
Well, a lot of natural gas
حسناً، الكثير من الغاز الطبيعي
and a little bit of nuclear, for starters.
والقليل من الطاقة النووية، كبداية.
And what goes on in the future?
وما الذي سيحصل في المستقبل؟
Well, I think out ahead of us a few decades
حسناً، أعتقد أن أمامنا بضعة عقود
is peak gas,
والغاز في الذروة،
and beyond that,
وأبعد من ذلك،
peak renewables.
ذروة الطاقة المتجددة.
Now, I'll tell you another little, very important
الآن، سأخبركم بقصة أخرى صغيرة
story about this picture.
مهمة للغاية حول هذه الصورة.
Now, I'm not pretending that energy use in total
الآن، أنا أمثّل أن إستخدام الطاقة في المجموع
isn't increasing, it is --
لا يتزايد، إنها تتزايد.
that's another part of the story. Come talk to me about it,
ذلك جزء آخر من القصة. تعالوا وتحدثوا معي حولها.
we'll fill in some of the details --
ويمكن أن نقدم بعض التفاصيل.
but there's a very important message here:
لكن توجد رسالة مهمة للغاية هنا.
This is 200 years of history,
هذه هي 200 سنة من التاريخ.
and for 200 years we've been systematically decarbonizing
وطوال 200 سنة، كنا نقوم بإزالة الكربون بمنهجية
our energy system.
من نظام طاقتنا.
Energy systems of the world
أنظمة الطاقة في العالم،
becoming progressively -- year on year,
تصبح متقدمة، سنة بعد سنة،
decade on decade, century on century --
عقد بعد عقد، قرن بعد قرن،
becoming less carbon intense.
تصبح أقل كثافة للكربون.
And that continues into the future
وذلك يتواصل إلى المستقبل
with the renewables that we're developing today,
مع الطاقة المتجددة التي نقوم بتطويرها اليوم،
reaching maybe 30 percent of primary energy
حتى نصل لحوالي 30% من إحتياجاتنا الأساسية للطاقة
by mid century.
بحلول منتصف القرن.
Now that might be the end of the story --
الآن ذلك قد يكون نهاية القصة --
Okay, we just replace it all with conventional renewables --
حسناً، نحن فقط نستبدلها بكل الطاقة المتجددة التقليدية--
but I think, actually, there's more to the story than that.
لكني أعتقد، في الواقع، أن هناك قصة أكثر بكثير من ذلك.
And to tell the next part of the story --
ولأخبركم بالجزء القادم من القصة --
and this is looking out say 2100 and beyond.
وهذا ينظر إلى بعيد، فلنقل أبعد من عام 2100.
What is the future
ما هو المستقبل
of truly sustainable, carbon-free energy?
لطاقة مستدامة حقاً، وخالية من إنبعاثات الكربون؟
Well, we have to take a little excursion,
حسناً، ينبغي علينا أخذ راحة صغيرة.
and we'll start in central Texas.
وسنبدأ في منتصف ولاية تكساس.
Here's a piece of limestone.
ها هي قطعة من الحجر الجيري.
I picked it up outside of Marble Falls, Texas.
قمت بالتقاطها من خارج ماربل فولس، تكساس.
It's about 400 million years old.
عمرها حوالي 400 مليون سنة.
And it's just limestone, nothing really special about it.
وهي مجرد حجر جيري، لا شئ مميز حولها.
Now, here's a piece of chalk.
الآن، ها هي قطعة طباشير.
I picked this up at MIT. It's a little younger.
لقد أخذتها من جامعة M.I.T. وهي أصغر عمراً .
And it's different than this limestone, you can see that.
وهي تفرق عن هذا الحجر الجيري. يمكنكم رؤية ذلك.
You wouldn't build a building out of this stuff,
لن تقوم ببناء بناية من هذه الأشياء،
and you wouldn't try to give a lecture and write on the chalkboard with this.
ولن تقوم بتقديم محاضرة وتحاول الكتابة على السبورة بهذه.
Yeah, it's very different -- no, it's not different.
نعم، إنها مختلفتان. لا، ليسا مختلفتان.
It's not different, it's the same stuff:
إنها لا تفرق. إنها نفس الشئ،
calcium carbonate, calcium carbonate.
كربونات الكالسيوم وكربونات الكالسيوم
What's different is how the molecules are put together.
الذي يفرق هو كيفية وضع الجزيئات معاً.
Now, if you think that's kind of neat,
الآن، إن كنت تفكر بهذه الأناقة،
the story gets really neat right now.
فالقصة تصبح بالفعل أنيقة الآن.
Off the coast of California comes this:
قبالة ساحل كالفورنيا، يأتي هذا.
It's an abalone shell.
إنها أُذن بحرية.
Now, millions of abalone every year
الآن، ملايين من "أذن البحر" سنوياً
make this shell.
تصنع هذه الصدفة.
Oh, by the way, just in case you weren't already guessing,
أوه، بالمناسبة، في حالة لم تكونوا قد خمنتم بعد،
it's calcium carbonate.
إنها كربونات الكالسيوم.
It's the same stuff as this
إنها نفس الشئ كهذا
and the same stuff as this.
ونفس الشئ كهذا.
But it's not the same stuff; it's different.
لكنهم ليسوا نفس الشئ. إنهم مختلفون.
It's thousands of times,
إنها آلالاف المرات.
maybe 3,000 times tougher than this.
ربما 3000 مرة أقوى من هذا.
And why? Because the lowly abalone
ولماذا؟ لأن أذن البحر المتواضع
is able to lay down
قادر على وضع
the calcium carbonate crystals in layers,
بلورات كربونات الكالسيوم في طبقات،
making this beautiful, iridescent
صانعاً هذا اللؤلؤ الجميل
mother of pearl.
القزحي الألوان.
Very specialized material
مواد متخصصة جداً
that the abalone self-assembles,
حيث أن أذن البحر تجمّع نفسها،
millions of abalone,
ملايين من أذن البحر،
all the time, every day, every year.
طوال الوقت، يومياً، سنوياً.
This is pretty incredible stuff.
هذا شئ مدهش للغاية.
All the same, what's different?
جميعها نفس الشئ، ما هو الفرق؟
How the molecules are put together.
كيفية وضع الجزيئات سوياً.
Now, what does this have to do with energy?
الآن، ما علاقة هذا بالطاقة؟
Here's a piece of coal.
ها هي قطعة فحم.
And I'll suggest that this coal
وسأقترح أن هذا الفحم
is about as exciting
مثير مثل
as this chalk.
هذه الطباشيرة.
Now, whether we're talking about fuels
الآن، سواء كنا نتحدث حول الوقود،
or energy carriers,
أو ناقلات الطاقة،
or perhaps novel materials for batteries
أو ربما مواد متكاملة للبطاريات
or fuel cells,
أو خلايا الوقود،
nature hasn't ever built those perfect materials yet
لم تقم الطبيعة ببناء تلك المواد المصقولة بعد،
because nature didn't need to.
لأن الطبيعة ليست في حاجة لها.
Nature didn't need to because, unlike the abalone shell,
الطبيعة ليست في حاجة لها بسبب، بخلاف صدف أذن البحر،
the survival of a species didn't depend
فان نجاة الأنواع لا تعتمد
on building those materials,
على بناء تلك المواد
until maybe now when it might just matter.
حتى الآن ربما، حينما قد تكون مجرد مواد.
So, when we think about the future of energy,
إذاً، عندما تفكر حول مستقبل الطاقة،
imagine
تخيّل،
what would it be like
ماذا سيكون
if instead of this,
إذا، عوضاً عن هذا،
we could build the energy equivalent of this
يمكننا بناء طاقة مكافئة لهذا،
just by rearranging the molecules differently.
فقط بإعادة ترتيب الجزيئات بصورة مختلفة.
And so that is my story.
ولذا فتلك هي قصتي.
The oil will never run out.
النفط لن ينتهي مطلقاً.
It's not because we have a lot of it.
ليس لأن لدينا الكثير منه.
It's not because we're going to build a bajillion windmills.
ليس لأننا سنقوم ببناء طواحين هواء ضخمة جداً.
It's because, well,
بل لأنه، حسناً،
thousands of years ago,
قبل آلالاف السنين،
people invented ideas --
أبتكر الناس الأفكار،
they had ideas, innovations, technology --
كان لديهم الأفكار، الإبتكارات، التكنلوجيات.
and the Stone Age ended,
وأنتهى العصر الحجري،
not because we ran out of stones.
ليس لأن الأحجار قد أنتهت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's ideas, it's innovation, it's technology
إنها فكرة، إنها إبتكار، إنها تكنلوجيا
that will end the age of oil, long before we run out of oil.
التي ستنهي عصر النفط قبل زمن طويل من نفاذ نفطنا.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)